So
于是
this week Vladimir Putin in
本周，弗拉基米尔·普京在
a speech said to his Russian people
一次演讲中对他的俄罗斯人民说
that
那
all of Russia must now
全俄必已准备好迎接全面战争。
prepare for total war.
Even if you are not fighting on the front lines in Ukraine,
即使你不在乌克兰前线作战，也请你假装在前线。
pretend you are.
因为这次演讲，许多分析家。
And because of this speech, there are many analysts
who believe that
谁认为
Putin is preparing Russia for total war.
普京正在把俄罗斯准备成总战状态。
And total war means that
而总战意味着
every aspect of your society is geared towards winning a war.
你的社会各个方面都已调动为赢得战争
And so we last had total war in World War II, okay?
于是我们在第二次世界大战中经历了总战，明白吗？
But not after that.
但之后就没有了。
So why is Putin doing this?
那为什么普京会这么做？
Now, there are some people who believe that
现在，有些人认为
it's because Russia is not doing so well in Ukraine.
这就是因为俄罗斯在乌克兰的表现不佳。
They lack manpower and so
他们缺乏人力，因此需要动员社会全力赢得乌克兰战争。
they need to mobilize their society to fully win the war in Ukraine.
好的？还有一个解释是…
Okay? Another explanation is
that Putin knows
那普京知道
that
那
NATO is preparing to send reinforcements to Ukraine.
北约正准备向乌克兰增援
Remember that because of last summer's offensive,
记住，因去年夏季的进攻，乌克兰人手不足。
Ukraine is desperately short of manpower.
现在他们的士兵平均年龄已超过四十岁。
Okay? The average age of their soldiers right now is over 40.
好吧？
They have men in their 60s who are fighting in the front lines.
他们有60多岁的士兵在前线作战。
Emmanuel Macron of France has publicly stated
法国总统马克龙公开表示
that he is considering sending French troops to Ukraine.
他正在考虑派遣法军前往乌克兰。
The British themselves are thinking of conscription,
英国人也在考虑征兵，把所有年轻人都调入军队。
drafting all young men into the army.
美国政客们说过…
The American politicians have said
that they're considering a new law that
他们正在考虑一项新法案，将为参军的非法移民授予国籍。
would give citizenship to illegal immigrants who join the army.
好的？所以看起来北约只会把乌克兰战争再推向前方。
Okay? So it seems like NATO is only going to escalate the war in Ukraine.
好的？
And so Russia is preparing for that.
于是俄罗斯也在为此做准备。
One more explanation, one more possibility is
再给一个解释，再给一个可能性是
that Putin wants to expand the war.
普京想要把战争扩大。
Okay? So he knows he's winning in Ukraine.
好的？所以他知道自己在乌克兰赢了。
He's thinking about attacking Moldova
他正在考虑进攻摩尔多瓦
and possibly the Baltic states.
以及可能的波罗国家。
Okay? These are all possibilities. Today,
好的？这些都是可能性。今天，
this morning, what I want to do is argue another possibility,
今晨，我想做的是再论一个可能性。
which is that
即是
Putin is mobilizing his society
普京正在动员他的社会
because he sees war as a tool,
因为他把战争视为工具，
as a mechanism,
作为一种机制，
to radically reshape
彻底重塑
the people in Russia.
俄罗斯人民
Okay? So think of a metaphor.
好的？那就想象成一个隐喻。
Okay? You're fat and you're like, okay,
好的？你又胖又说，好吧。
how do I get fit?
我怎么变得健壮？
How do I get trim? Right? You go to the gym and you work out.
我怎么变得苗条？对吧？你去健身房练习。
And for Putin, that's what war is.
对普京来说，战争就是这样。
War is a workout for society.
战争是社会的锻炼。
When you enter war, you become a much more disciplined, unified,
当你投身战争，你会变得更有纪律、更统一。
and prosperous society.
和繁荣的社会。
Okay? So that's what I want to argue today.
好吧。今天我要论证的就是这个。
Okay. So why does Putin think like this?
好的。那么普京为什么会这么想呢？
Well, let's look at the current state of Russia.
好了，先来看看俄罗斯的现状。
Okay? Russia, in many aspects, is a broken society. Corruption.
好？在许多方面，俄罗斯是一个破碎的社会。腐败。
Russia is the most corrupt society in all of Europe.
俄罗斯是欧洲最腐败的社会。
The rich people, steal,
富人们偷走，
and then they run off to Europe or the United States or Dubai.
然后他们跑到欧洲、美国或迪拜去
Okay? So corruption is a huge problem in Russia.
好？所以腐败是俄罗斯的一个大问题
And because of corruption, the GDP of Russia is very low.
因为腐败，俄罗斯的GDP很低。
So South Korea, which has about a third of the population of Russia,
韩国人口约为俄罗斯的三分之一，GDP更高。
has a higher GDP. Okay?
好？
The state of Texas, this one state in the United States, has a higher GDP than Russia.
德州是美国的一个州，GDP比俄罗斯高。
So Russia, in many ways, in many respects, is a very poor country.
俄国在许多方面、许多层面上是一个非常贫穷的国家。
Okay? Second problem is alcoholism.
第二个问题是酿酒。
One out of every six Russian males,
每六名俄罗斯男性中有一人
about 16, 17% of the population,
约占人口的16、17%
they're alcoholics.
他们是酒鬼
Okay? It's a disease.
好的？这是一种病。
They have the disease of alcoholism.
他们患有酿酒病。
One out of every three deaths in Russia is
俄罗斯每三起死亡中就有一人。
because of drinking too much.
因为喝酒太多。
And because of alcoholism,
以及因为酿酒病，
the rate of young men
年轻男性的比率
dying is just increasing and increasing.
死亡率只在不断上升。
Okay? The third problem is fertility.
好吧？第三个问题是出生率。
So right now, the fertility rate in Russia is 1.5.
现在，俄罗斯的出生率是1.5。
That is below the replacement level.
低于替代水平。
Right? Remember that the replacement level for society is 2.1.
对吧？记得替代水平是2.1。
Russia is 1.5.
俄罗斯是1.5。
But probably you have a lot of men dying because of alcoholism.
但大概你会有很多人因酗酒而去世。
Okay? So since the year 2000,
好吧？自2000年以来，俄罗斯人口一直在稳步下降。
the population in Russia has been declining steadily.
And all this means is that
这意味着……
if current trends continue,
如果趋势继续……
then Russia will cease to exist as a society.
那么俄罗斯将不再是一个社会。
Okay? The nation will die.
好的？民族国家会消亡。
So why is this happening?
那为什么会这样呢？
Well, okay. The Western explanation is,
嗯，好吧。西方的解释是，
is that this is happening because
这就是因为……
Russia is not democratic.
俄罗斯不是民主的。
Right? If you have full democracy and
好的吗？如果你拥有完整的民主并且…
you unleash the human potential
你释放你们人民的潜能，俄罗斯就会繁荣。
of your people, then
Russia will prosper.
你释放你们人民的潜能，俄罗斯就会繁荣。
But Putin, Vladimir Putin, has a different explanation.
但普京，弗拉基米尔·普京，有一个不同的解释。
Okay? His explanation is that this is happening to Russia.
好的？他的解释是，这一切发生在俄罗斯。
Okay? Corruption, alcoholism, and low fertility
好的？腐败、酿酒和低出生率。
because Russians have been lied to,
因为俄罗斯人被西方文明欺骗，
deceived,
被欺骗，
and manipulated by Western civilization.
被操纵。
Western civilization preaches the gospel of liberal democracy,
西方文明宣讲自由民主的福音，
of freedom, of human rights, of consumerism.
自由、人的权利、消费主义的。
And these are all lies.
而这些都是谎言。
They're hypocrisies that have fooled the Russian people
这些是让俄罗斯人上当的伪善
and have corrupted the Russian soul
并玷污了俄罗斯灵魂
and destroyed Russian civilization.
并毁灭了俄罗斯文明。
And because Russians are abandoning their soul,
而且因为俄罗斯人正在放弃他们的灵魂
their civilization, their nation,
他们的文明，他们的民族国家
this is why this is happening.
这就是事情发生的原因。
Okay? Does that make sense? That is Putin's argument.
好的？这样说通吗？这就是普京的论点。
So why does Putin believe this?
那为什么普京会这么认为？
Well, in the late 80s,
好吧，在80年代末，
the Soviet Union had basically lost the Cold War.
苏联基本上已输掉冷战。
And they lost the Cold War because their elite basically gave up.
他们因为精英基本放弃而输掉冷战。
They no longer believed in communism.
他们不再相信共产主义。
They didn't believe in self -sacrifice for the nation.
他们不再相信为民族自我牺的精神。
They thought that Western values,
他们认为西方价值观，
the Western lifestyle was much better.
西方生活方式更好。
Okay? So they gave up. In the late 80s,
好吧？于是他们放弃了。
there was an American historian.
有一位美国历史学家。
He actually works for the American State Department.
他实际上在美国国务院工作。
And his name is Francis Fukuyama.
他的名字是弗朗西斯·福山。
And he wrote an extremely
他还写了一篇极。
influential essay called The End of History.
一篇名为《历史的终结》的有影响力的论文。
End of History.
历史的终结。
Okay? With a quotation mark.
“好吧？”
And he argued that
他认为
the Soviet Union fell
苏联解体
and America became triumphant because liberal democracy
美国因自由民主而胜利
is the best idea
是最好的想法
to have ever been invented.
曾经发明的。
And to make his argument,
并为此作出论点。
he uses the philosopher Frederick Hegel.
他引用了哲学家弗里德里希·黑格。
Okay? Now, Frederick Hegel had something called the theory of the dialectic.
好的？现在，弗里德里希·黑格有一种叫做辩证法的理论。
Dialectic. And
辩证法。
what Hegel argued is that history
何塞格所论的，是历史由思想之战决定的。
is determined by a war of ideas.
历史的进程由思想的运动决定。
The progress of history is determined by the movement of ideas.
And how ideas work is
并且思想的运作方式是
that they have a pattern called the dialectic.
它们有一种叫做辩证法的模式。
Okay? So there's a thesis.
好的？于是出现了一个命题。
A new idea comes into being.
出现一个新想法。
But then we recognize that this idea has problems.
随后我们发现这个想法有问题。
It's too extreme. It's too problematic.
它太极端，太棘手。
So we create an antithesis.
于是我们提出了一个对立命题。
Okay? But
好？但……
this antithesis itself is also too extreme.
这个对立命题本身也太极端。
And this creates also problems. So then
于是又产生了问题。于是……
what happens is the thesis and antithesis come together
随后，正题与反题相遇……
and create a more moderate, more efficient idea.
并形成更中庸、更高效的想法。
Okay? Called the synthesis.
好？称之为合成。
And this is how
而这就是……
history moves or progresses.
历史的运动或进展方式。
And so Fukuyama takes this idea and says, okay,
于是福山把这个想法拿来说，好的，
well this explains what's happening today.
好吧，这就解释了现在的情况。
Where at first you have a thesis called capitalism.
首先你有一个叫做资本主义的正题。
Okay? Capitalism.
好？资本主义。
And this creates the industrial revolution.
而这造就工业革命。
Right? And because capitalism was too extreme,
对吧，因资本主义过度，
we move towards communism.
我们向共产主义前进。
Okay? Communism was created
好？共产主义是被创造出来的。
to counteract the extremes of capitalism.
以抵消资本主义的极端。
But communism itself is too extreme.
但共产主义本身过于极端。
So then we move towards the middle.
于是我们转向中间。
Which is the right idea.
这才是正确的想法。
Which is called liberal democracy.
哪种叫做自由民主。
Okay? So what is liberal democracy? Well,
好？那自由民主是什么？嗯，
at the core of liberal democracy is the idea of consumerism.
自由民主的核心是消费主义的观念。
And the idea of consumerism is that we exist
并且消费主义的想法是我们存在的目的是买东西。
to buy things.
只要我们买东西，…。
And as long as we buy things,
there will be world peace.
将会有世界和平。
Why? Because consumers have the right to buy things.
为什么？因为消费者有买东西的权利。
And they have a need to buy. And therefore
他们也有买东西的需求，因此。
nations have a need to produce.
国家有生产的需求。
And nations produce the best when
当国家相互贸易而非互战时，生产最为出色。
they are trading together as opposed to warring against each other.
Okay? So this is the argument
好的？这就是弗朗西斯·福山在“历史终结”中提出的论点。
that Francis Fukuyama makes in the end of history.
我想进一步阐述这个论点。
I want to explain this argument further.
Okay? What's he really saying?
好的？他到底在说什么？
Okay. So throughout human history,
好的。所以在人的历史中，
all societies have struggled with one problem.
所有社会都在与同一个问题作斗争。
Which is how do we optimize
哪是我们如何优化劳动力？
the workforce? How do we get each and
我们怎样让每个人都尽可能努力工作？
every person to work as hard as possible for our society?
让每个人都为我们的社会尽力工作？
And if everyone did that, then our society would be
如果每个人都这么做，我们的社会就会强大、团结、繁荣。
strong, united, and prosperous.
对吧？好吧？所以这就是政治的根本问题。
Right? Okay? So that's a fundamental problem of politics.
How do we optimize workforce participation?
我们怎样优化劳动力参与？
And traditionally, or historically, there have been three answers.
传统上，或历史上，已有三种答案。
The first is war.
第一种是战争。
The second is religion.
第二种是宗教。
And the third is civilization.
第三种是文明。
Okay? Now,
好吧？
as you can understand,
正如你所理解，
these three things work because they give
这三件事之所以奏效，是因为它们赋予了
structure, meaning,
结构、意义，
and purpose to our lives.
并且赋予我们生活的目的。
Okay? And we have structure, meaning, and purpose,
好吧？我们有结构、意义和目的，
we are much more motivated to work hard.
我们就更有动力去努力工作。
But as you can also see, there are actually lots of problems
但正如你所见，三者都有不少问题。
with all three.
对吧？战争就是杀人。
Right? War is you kill people.
That's bad. Religion is superstitious.
那就糟了。宗教是迷信。
Okay? But civilization itself is also
好吧？但文明本身也是
problematic. Because the larger extreme of civilization is
问题的。因为文明的更大极限是
racism. Okay? Which
种族主义。好吧？就是要说我们俄罗斯人比其他人好。
is to say that we Russians are better than everyone else.
我们中国人比其他人好。
We Chinese are better than everyone else.
Therefore, we can do whatever we want.
于是我们可以随心所欲。
Okay? And this naturally leads to imperialism. Right?
好吧？这自然导致了帝国主义。对吧？
We have a duty to go conquer other people,
我们有义务去征服他人。
to civilize them.
把他们文明化。
Right? Something called the white man's burden.
对吧？这叫白人负担。
And this leads to fascism.
于是就出现了法西主义。
Okay? Okay?
好吧？好吧？
War and conquest are the ultimate good.
战争与征服是终极之善。
So, historically, war, religion, and civilization
于是，历史上，战争、宗教与文明。
have given people structure, meaning, and purpose,
给人们结构、意义和目的。
but they create a lot of problems.
但它们造成了很多问题。
They create suffering, and war,
它们带来痛苦与战争。
and pain. Okay?
和痛苦。好吧？
So, but over time,
于是，随着时间的推移，
what has happened is that
发生的事是……
all of them, over time, have become much more abstract.
它们都在时间里变得更抽象。
And the reason why they've become more abstract is in order to increase the population,
原因是为了增加人口
in order to create mass society.
以此形成大众社会
Okay? So, let me give you an example of this.
好的？那么，我给你举个例子。
The earliest religions
最早的宗教
in humanity have been polytheistic.
在人类中曾是多神论。
Okay? And the gods themselves were very much like humans.
好的？而神们本身也很像人。
Think of the Greeks. Okay? Zeus,
想想希腊人。好吧？宙斯，
Athena, Hera.
雅典娜，赫拉。
Okay? It was a polytheistic society, and
好吧？那是一个多神论社会，且
they were very much like humans.
它们非常像人类。
But over time,
但随着时间的推移，
this polytheism became monotheistic, and it became abstract.
这多神论演变为单神论，并变得抽象。
Okay? The idea of God was so much removed from us.
好的？神的概念从我们身上已远去。
And the benefit of that is that
而且那样的好处是
you can have more people believing in one God.
你可以让更多人相信一位神。
And it motivates you to work harder.
这激励你更努力工作。
Okay? It's just an abstract concept.
好的？它只是一个抽象概念。
And because of abstraction,
而且因为抽象化，
we develop new ideas.
我们发展新想法。
For example, money.
例如，金钱。
Okay? So,
好吧？所以，
rather than have war, religion,
不如有战争，宗教，
and civilization as the structure
并且文明作为结构和我们社会的中心，便会产生金钱。
and center of our society, one would make money
from the structure of your society. Okay?
从你们社会的结构中。好吧？
This is what we call capitalism.
这就是我们所说的资本主义。
And capitalism, of course, led to the industrial revolution.
资本主义当然也导致了工业革命。
Industrialism. Okay?
工业主义。好吧？
Capitalism meant that societies were becoming
资本主义意味着社会正在变得…
wealthier and wealthier, more industrialized.
更富裕、更富裕，工业化程度更高。
Okay? Does that make sense? Alright.
好吧？这有道理吗？好的。
But there's a problem with capitalism. Right?
但资本主义有个问题。对吧。
What's the problem with making capital or money at the very heart of your society?
在你社会的核心制造资本或金钱有什么问题？
Exactly. Okay? So,
好的？那么，
the first major problem with capitalism is it's all -consuming.
资本主义的第一个主要问题是它的全盘消耗。
So, as Jack says,
于是正如杰克所说，
all capitalism cares about is the expansion and
资本主义所关心的全是资本的扩张与增长，
growth of capital, regardless of its effect on society.
不管它对社会的影响如何。
Okay? Profit for the sake of growing profit.
好的？利润只为利润而增长。
It's an all -consuming idea, which
这是一种全盘消耗的想法，且
can ultimately lead to the destruction of the planet.
最终可能导致地球的毁灭。
Okay? That's the first problem.
好的？那是第一个问题。
What's another problem with capitalism?
资本主义还有什么别的问题？
Or the idea of having money as the heart and center of your society?
或者把钱当作你们社会的心脏和中心的想法呢？
Anyone? Okay. So,
有人吗？好的。于是，
what this means is that
这意味着什么呢，
money likes to consolidate itself.
钱喜欢自我合并。
Okay? Consolidating. Okay? Meaning that
好的？合并。好的？意思是……
if, so the example is, let's just say that each of us had a million dollars.
如果，举个例子，假设我们每人都有一百万美元。
Right? What's the fastest way for us to grow our money?
好的？最快让我们钱增值的方法是什么？
If we put it together, right? And then we go invest it.
如果我们把它们放在一起，好的？然后我们去投资它。
Okay? So, in other words, if you just like,
好的？所以，换句话说，如果你只是……
let capitalism do whatever it wants to infinity,
让资本主义做它想做的事，直到无穷无尽。
what happens is that you exactly have one person with all the money.
发生的事是，你恰好拥有一个人掌握所有的钱。
Okay? Does that make sense? Because that's the fastest way to grow money, by consolidating it.
好的？这样说通吗？因为这就是通过合并最快让钱增值的方式。
Okay? So that's problematic. What else is wrong with
好的？所以这就有问题。还有什么不对的地方？
capitalism or money? Okay.
资本主义还是金钱？好的。
So another problem is the idea of alienating.
另一个问题是异化的概念。
Or dehumanizing.
或者去人性化。
Okay? What does this mean?
好的？这句话是什么意思？
Capital alienates and dehumanizes.
资本使人异化并去人性化。
What does that mean?
那又是什么意思？
Exactly. Okay. You are, you as a person cease to be human.
正是。好的。你，作为一个人，便不再是人类。
Right? To be human is to be a complex,
对吗？成为人类就是成为一个复杂的，
multifaceted individual
多面向的个体。
who likes to create and love.
谁喜欢创造并热爱。
But in capitalism, you're only your production value,
但在资本主义里，你只是自己的生产价值，
you're only the amount of money in your bank account.
你只是银行账户里的金额。
Okay? Does that make sense? Alright?
好的？这样说通吗？好吧？
So, for all these reasons,
所以，基于这些原因，
capitalism is really bad.
资本主义真的很糟。
There are actually more reasons. Okay? So, Karl Marx,
有更多理由。好吧？于是，卡尔·马克思在《共产党宣言》中指出了资本主义的这些问题，并提出了解决方案。
in his Communist Manifesto, points out all these problems of capitalism
在他的《共产党宣言》中，卡尔·马克思指出了资本主义的这些问题，并提出了解决方案。
and he proposes a solution.
卡尔·马克思在《共产党宣言》中指出了资本主义的这些问题，并提出了解决方案。
Which is, okay, rather than make money at the heart
哪是，好的，先在工业社会的中心而不是赚钱
and center of your industrial society,
在工业社会的中心，先是工人而不是赚钱
make the worker the heart
把工人放在工业社会的中心
and center of your society.
在你的社会中心。
Okay? So he makes this argument.
好的？于是他提出了这个论点。
But what's very revolutionary or prescient
但这到底是什么革命性或先见之处。
about his argument is this is a natural cycle.
关于他的论点是这是一个自然循环。
Okay? This is part of the Hegel cycle where capitalism comes along and
好的？这属于黑格循环的一部分，资本主义出现并且会出现。
capitalism will be the natural evolution
资本主义将是自然演进。
of capitalism. Okay?
资本主义的。好的吗？
Why? Okay.
为什么？好的吗。
Okay. So let's do the thought experiment.
好。于是我们来做这个思考实验。
Okay? Let's do this thought experiment where your parents have died
好的？让我们做这个思考实验：你的父母去世了。
and now you're working in a factory in order to survive.
然后你去工厂工作以求生计。
How do you feel about this?
你对此有何感受？
Your parents have died. There's no one to support you.
你的父母去世了，没人能扶持你。
So, at age 16, 17, 18, you have to go off to a factory.
于是你在十六、十七、十八岁时得去工厂。
To make money for yourself.
在那里为自己赚钱。
So how do you feel about this?
你对此有何感受？
Are you happy about this?
你对此感到开心吗？
How, how do you feel?
你是怎么想的？
Depressing and? And lonely and?
沮丧又？又孤单？
Yeah, exactly. You're bitter.
是的，正是。你很酸涩。
And you're depressed.
而且你很沮丧。
Okay? You're alienated.
好的？你已疏离。
So then what do you do? Then what do you do?
那你接着干什么？那你接着干什么？
What can you do now? You're bitter.
你现在能干什么？你很酸涩。
You're angry. You're depressed.
你生气了。你沮丧。
You're lonely. So what do you do?
你孤单。那你干什么？
Okay. You start to
好了。你开始
think about why this is the case.
想想为什么会这样。
Right? You start to have a political consciousness.
对吧？你开始有了政治意识。
What Marx calls political
马克思所说的政治…
consciousness. From this alienation of the worker,
意识。由工人离化产生，从而产生意识。
workers will start to develop a political consciousness.
工人将开始形成政治意识。
Right? They're like, why is this happening?
对吧？他们会问，为什么会这样？
Why has the government abandoned me?
政府为什么抛弃我？
Why has society abandoned me?
社会为什么抛弃我？
What can I do about this?
我能对此做些什么？
Okay? So then what happens?
好的？那接下来会怎样？
That's exactly right. You want change.
完全正确。你想要改变。
Right? And how do you enact change?
对了？你怎么去实现改变？
Yes. Okay. You spread your ideas and you organize.
是的。好的。你传播你的想法并组织起来。
Right? And when you organize, what do you realize?
对了？当你组织时，你会意识到什么？
Yeah. What you recognize when you start to organize is
是的。你开始组织时所认识到的事是…
the capitalist needs you to do the work.
资本家需要你来做工作。
Right? The capitalist owns the capital and
对了？资本家拥有资本和工厂，...
the factories, but you're the one who's actually doing the real work.
...但你才是实际做工作的人。
So without you,
所以没有你，
the factories can't run. So as long as you stay united,
工厂就运转不了。只要你们保持统一，
you can enact whatever political demands you want.
你们就能实现任何你们想要的政治诉求。
Okay? Does that make sense? Okay?
好的？这样说通吗？好？
So for Marx, this is just a natural evolution of capitalism.
于是对马克思来说，这只是资本主义的自然演变。
Capitalism leads to the alienation of the working class,
资本主义导致工人阶级的异化。
which will lead to their political consciousness, which will lead to their solidarity,
这将导致他们的政治意识，随后产生团结，并引发政治革命，于是工人便成为核心与中心。
which will lead to a political revolution, and
so you can make the worker as the heart and center
这将导致他们的政治意识，随后产生团结，并引发政治革命，于是工人便成为核心与中心。
of your society.
你的社会的……
Okay? Does that make sense, guys?
好吧？这样说通吗，大家？
Alright? Now,
好了？现在，
what's amazing about Marx
马克思的惊人之处
is that today we say he's wrong.
就是今天我们说他错了。
Right? Communism happened in the Soviet Union,
对吧？共产主义在苏联出现了。
it happened in China, but it didn't happen in Europe and in the United States.
它发生在中国，但在欧洲和美国没有发生。
Where Marx said it would happen first, because
马克思说它会首先发生，因为
Germany was more industrialized than Russia or China.
德国比俄罗斯或中国更工业化。
Okay? Does that make sense? That's what we say.
好的？这有道理吗？这就是我们说的。
If you think about it deeply, okay,
如果你深思一下，好吗，
Marx was right. After World War II,
马克思是对的。二战后，
every society, every industrial society, to some extent,
每个社会、每个工业社会，在某种程度上，都采纳了共产主义的理想。
adopted the ideals of communism.
这有道理吗？好吗？
Does that make sense? Okay?
We call this socialism, not communism, but
我们称之为社会主义，而非共产主义，但
basically it adhere to the thinking
基本上它遵循马克思的思路，
of Marx, which is to make the worker the heart
即把工人放在核心位置。
and center of your society.
并成为你们社会的中心。
And why did they do that after World War II?
那为什么他们在第二次世界大战后这么做？
Exactly, okay? Because workers create value.
没错，好的？因为工人创造价值。
Money doesn't create any value.
钱本身不创造任何价值。
Money just creates more money.
钱只是再造钱。
Okay, it's speculative. But the workers create value.
好的，算是投机。可工人创造价值。
And therefore, you have to treat your workers properly.
于是，你就得好好对待你的工人。
So, in America and in Europe,
于是，在美国和欧洲，
workers became the heart and center of your society.
工人成为你们社会的心脏与中心。
And the workers through unions
并且工人通过工会
could demand political reforms.
可以要求政治改革
And so, all of society was geared towards making the lives of the middle class,
于是，整个社会都以中产阶层的生活为目标
the working class, better, okay?
工人，做得更好，行吗？
That's why you had excellent healthcare,
这就是你们拥有优质医疗的原因，
great public schools.
以及优秀的公立学校。
Cheap universities. Okay?
便宜的大学，行吗？
So, the 50s and 60s and 70s was basically the peak
于是，50年代、60年代、70年代基本是工人阶层社会的巅峰。
of society for the working class.
But in the 80s,
[402] 但在80年代，
we started to change this.
[403] 我们开始改变这一点。
Why? Why would we want to change the system?
[404] 为什么？我们为什么要改系统？
It's a great system, right? Marx is right.
它是个很棒的系统，对吧？马克思是对的。
Having the worker as the heart and center of your society.
把工人放在社会的心脏和中心。
As the central organizing unit of society
把工人作为社会的核心组织单元。
makes a lot more sense than having money as the heart
更有意义的是把钱放在心脏和中心，明白吗？
and center, okay? But starting in the 80s, we start to go back to money.
但从80年代开始，我们又把钱放回了心脏和中心。
Why? Excuse me?
为什么？请问一下？
Who wants more? Yes, exactly.
谁想要更多？是的，正是如此。
So, what happened in the 80s is something called the revolt of the elite.
于是，80年代发生的事叫做精英的反叛。
Okay? In other words,
对吗？换句话说，
the problem with having a society based on the worker is it becomes too egalitarian,
问题在于以工人为基础的社会会变得过于平等，
too equal, right?
太平等了，对吗？
But if you're like the elite, you don't want equality,
但如果你是精英，你就不想要平等，
you want difference.
你想要差异。
You want to have the same values.
你想拥有同样的价值观。
You want to have power and money in your hands.
你想把权力和金钱握在手中。
Does that make sense? So, the revolt of the elite happened in the 80s.
这有道理吗？于是精英的起义发生在80年代。
And this is what we call in the United States the Reagan Revolution,
这就是我们在美国称之为里根革命的事。
okay? The Reagan Revolution.
对吧？里根革命。
The beginning of neoliberalism, free market capitalism.
新自由主义的起点，自由市场资本主义。
And in Britain it was called Thatcherism, okay?
在英国被称为撒切尔主义，明白吗？
Margaret Thatcher. The Thatcher Revolution.
玛格丽特·撒切尔。撒切尔革命。
And so, now you need to transition
于是，现在你需要从工人转向别的角色，明白吗？
away from the worker to something else, okay?
再来一个新的意识形态，明白吗？
Another ideology that
Another ideologythat
allows the elite to amass power, okay?
让精英聚集力量，明白吗？
So, just to show you how radical this revolution was,
于是，为了展示这场革命的激进程度，
in the 1970s, okay?
在1970年代，明白吗？
In the 1970s, if you were a CEO, the head of a company, okay?
在1970年代，如果你是CEO，公司的负责人，明白吗？
You were making on average
你平均每年赚一百万美元。
one million US dollars a year.
That's pretty good, right? That's really good money.
那挺不错的，对吧？真是好钱。
And that one million dollars
而那一百万美元
was more than
刚刚好
20 times the worker.
20倍于工人。
Okay? And that's
好吧？而且是
pretty reasonable. Today,
相当合理。今天，
the average CEO in the United States
美国平均CEO年薪2000万美元
makes 20 million dollars a year.
他每年赚2000万美元
And that
而且是
is 200 to 300 times more than the average worker in the company.
比公司平均工人高200到300倍。
Does that make sense? So,
这样说对吗？所以，
in the 80s inequality started
80年代不平等开始。
to explode.
爆炸。
Right? And so, they're transitioning
对吧？于是他们从工人转向新的…
from the worker to a new
从工人到新的…
organizing unit called the consumer.
组织单元称为消费者。
Okay? So, they needed to destroy
好的？于是他们需要消灭
the working class, the middle class.
工人阶层与中产阶层。
And the way they did it was by introducing a new concept called the consumer, okay?
并且他们的做法是引入一个新概念叫做消费者，行吗？
So, in the 50s, 60s, and 70s, the government promised you a good job.
于是在50年代、60年代、70年代，政府向你承诺一份好工作。
If you were a member of a society if you were a citizen,
如果你是社会成员，若你是公民，
I promise you a good job
我向你承诺一份好工作
that you would have for the rest of your life.
你将拥有的工作将伴随你余生
Okay? So, in the 80s,
好吧？于是到了80年代
the government said I promise you that
政府说我向你承诺
you have low prices and a wide selection of goods.
你将享有低价和丰富的商品选择。
Okay? Does that make sense?
好吧？这样说通吗？
Alright? So, this sounds like a subtle shift,
好的？这听起来像是一个细微的转变，从工人到消费者。
going from the worker to the consumer.
好的？但这意味着一次革命。
Okay? But what this meant was a revolution
好的？这听起来像是一个细微的转变，从工人到消费者。
in society. A revolution in politics.
在社会中。政治上的革命。
So, remember that an example of the worker,
记住，工人是个例子，
the worker has to have political consciousness in order to protect his or her rights,
工人必须有政治意识，才能保护自己的权利。
in order to organize and unify
为组织和统一而行动，并推动有利的政治改革。
and push for favorable political reforms.
好的？这就是工人要做的事。
Okay? That's what the worker must do.
Okay? That's whatthe worker must do.
Okay? But now let's think about the mentality of the consumer.
好的？现在让我们思考消费者的心态。
And to do this, let's do another
接着来做一次新的思维实验。
thought experiment. And the thought experiment is this.
思维实验的内容是这样：
Everyone in the school, about 500 people,
学校里的人大约五百人，
I decide to give everyone 1 million US dollars.
我决定给每人一百万美元。
Okay? So, everyone in the school
好吧？于是，学校里的人们。
has exactly 1 million US dollars
恰好有一百万美元
to spend. What happens now?
要花费。现在会怎样？
Think about this. What happens now?
想想这个。现在会怎样？
Use your imagination. What happens?
用你的想象力。接下来会怎样？
What's the first thing you do? What's the first thing you do? I've given you a million dollars.
第一件事是什么？第一件事是什么？我给了你一百万美元。
What do you do with it? Well,
你用它做什么？好吧…
the first thing you do is buy something, right?
第一件事是买点东西，对吧？
What do you want to buy? A 1 million dollars is a lot of money.
你想买什么？一百万美元是很多钱。
What do you want to buy, Nav?
你想买什么，Nav？
You buy a house. You buy a house, right?
你买一栋房子。你买一栋房子，对吧？
That's great. That's a great purchase.
太好了。买得不错。
Then what do you do? Then what do you do?
接下来你做什么？接下来你做什么？
Then buy a house.
然后买一栋房子。
Then buy furniture.
然后买家具。
Okay. First thing is Nav buys a house.
好的。第一件事是Nav买一栋房子。
Then what does he do? Buy furniture.
然后他做什么？买家具。
Buy furniture. Then what does he do?
买家具。然后他做什么？
There's something that he must do that's very important.
有件事他必须做，十分重要。
What does he buy the house?
他买的房子是什么？
What does he want to do? He wants to take pictures
他想做什么？他想拍照
and post on social media.
并在社交媒体上发布
Right? So everyone sees it on social media.
对吧？于是大家都能在社交媒体上看到。
Then you see this.
然后你就会看到这个。
Nav has this huge house in Beijing with lots of fancy furniture.
Nav在北京有一座大房子，里面摆满了豪华家具。
What do you do now? You also want to buy a house.
你现在做什么？你也想买房子。
But what kind of house? A bigger house, right?
但是什么样的房子？更大的房子，对吧？
And then what do you do? You also post pictures.
然后你又做什么？你也会发照片。
You also post pictures, okay? Then how do other people feel?
你也会发照片，好的？那其他人会怎么感觉？
You think this is funny, okay?
你觉得这很有趣，好的？
But this happens all the time. So
但这件事一直发生着。
very quickly what happens in the school?
很快学校里发生了什么？
And you all spend your money and you all go into debt.
你们都花钱，结果都欠债。
Right? Because you're in competition with each other.
对吧？因为你们互相竞争。
That's not the biggest thing. And one million dollars is a lot of money but
那不是最重要的事。百万美元算不少，但也买不完所有东西，对吧？
it's not enough to buy everything, right?
于是你们又欠债。你们再借钱买更多东西。然后又会发生什么？
So you go into debt. You borrow more money to buy more things. And then what happens?
So you go into debt. You borrow more moneyto buy more things. And then what happens?
And then what happens? How do you guys feel about each other?
然后发生什么？你们彼此之间的感受如何？
Do you guys have lunch together? Do you guys have dinner together?
你们一起吃午饭吗？一起吃晚饭吗？
Do you guys like to share homework together?
你们喜欢一起做作业吗？
Do you guys like to share homework together? You guys hate each other, right?
你们喜欢一起做作业吗？你们彼此相互嫌吗？
At the end of the day what will happen is you all go into debt and you all hate each other.
一天结束后，大家都会背债，互相仇恨。
Right? So that's consumerism.
对吧？这就是消费主义。
This is what consumerism is.
这就是消费主义。
Consumerism creates a competition
消费主义产生竞争。
in society in society for prestige,
在社会中为了声望而竞争，
okay? To see who can post the nicest social media pictures.
好吧？看看谁能发最漂亮的社交媒体照片。
This leads to the individualization
这导致了个体化
or the optimization
或优化
of you, okay?
你们的意思，好的？
In other words, you are now
换句话说，你们现在是
unable to act together.
无法一起行动。
You don't want to organize.
你不想组织。
You don't want to act in solidarity. Okay?
你不想团结行动。好吗？
And ultimately this means that
最终这意味着
you develop economic logic.
你发展经济逻辑。
Okay? And what is economic logic?
好的？那经济逻辑是什么？
It's to see the world
就是用经济逻辑去看世界。
only through the lens of capital.
仅通过资本的视角。
Okay? Does it make sense? So when you see someone
好？有道理吗？所以当你看到某人时，
and you're like, okay well, do I want to date this person?
你会想，好的，我想和他约会吗？
You don't ask, oh is this person a nice person?
你不问，哦，这个人是好人吗？
You ask yourself, how much money does this person have?
你问自己，这个人有多少钱？
Okay? You understand? You use economic logic in order to
好？你明白了吗？你用经济逻辑来……
understand the world and to reason and analyze the world, okay?
理解世界并进行推理与分析，明白了吗？
Now let me ask you this question.
现在让我问你这个问题。
Today is this how China works?
今天就是中国的运作方式吗？
Is this how the world works?
这就是世界运作的方式吗？
The answer is yes, okay?
答案是是，好的？
Are you like this?
你是这样的吗？
Yes, you are like this, okay?
是的，你就是这样，明白了吗？
You've been brainwashed into thinking
你已经被灌输成这样想法
that this is the only way to behave
这才是唯一的行为方式
and to think. You're in school.
并且思考。你在学校。
Why are you in school? So
你为什么在学校？所以
you can get a good job. Why? To make money.
你能得到一份好工作。为什么？为了赚钱。
So you can buy things, okay? You understand?
所以你可以买东西，明白吗？你懂了吗？
That's how you all think. But there are different ways to think about school, right?
这就是你们的想法。但关于学校的思考方式还有别的，懂吗？
You're like, I'm in school to learn, to open my mind, to have an imagination,
我在学校是为了学习、开阔我的思维、拥有想象力。
to think critically about the world, right?
思考世界，没错吗？
Now it's a way we thought about school
现在它是我们思考学校的方式
when the workers were dominant.
当工人占主导时
But now that consumers are dominant,
但现在消费者占主导，我想的全是怎么找份好工作？
all we think about is how do I get a good job?
我怎么买更大的房子？
How do I buy a bigger house?
Because I want to post it on social media,
因为我想把它发到社交媒体上，
okay? So if you think about this,
好吧？所以如果你考虑这个，
what this really is
这到底是什么
is the perfection
是奴隶的完美
of slavery. Does it make sense?
奴隶的完美。是否有意义？
What does this phrase mean? The perfection of slavery?
这个短语是什么意思？奴隶的完美？
Yeah, you become a slave of the money, but what?
是的，你成了金钱的奴隶，那又怎样？
Why is this perfect? Yes,
为什么这很完美？是的，
okay? You understand? If you're a slave, you rebel,
好吧？你明白吗？如果你是奴隶，你就会反叛，
right? But if you don't know you're a slave and
对吧？但如果你不知道自己是奴隶而且你喜欢这样，你就会选择这样，
you like this, you choose this,
然后你就永不反叛，好吗？
then you will never rebel, okay?
So the consumerism
于是消费主义是奴役的完美，好的？
is the perfection
是消费主义的完美，好的？
of slavery, okay?
于是消费主义是奴役的完美，好的？
And you can't do that. You can't do that. That's why Francis Fukuyama thinks
而你做不到。你做不到。正因如此，福山富士雄认为
that consumerism is the end of
消费主义是历史的终点。因为它是一个系统。
history. Because it is a system
history. Becauseit is a system
that achieves what the elites want
实现精英所欲之事
and the masses are unwilling
而大众不愿亦不敢抗议
and unable to protest and rebel.
并且无力反抗
Okay, does that make sense? It's a perfect system.
好的，听得懂吗？这就是完美的系统。
Okay? So
好的？那么
but there are certain civilizations
但确实有些文明
that rebel against slavery
反抗奴役
intrinsically. It is in their nature to rebel against slavery.
本质如此，反抗奴役是其天性。
And one of these civilizations is the Russian civilization.
其中之一是俄国文明。
Okay? So when you impose slavery
好的？那么当你把奴役强加给俄国人时，他们就会腐败，
on Russians, they become corrupt,
他们就会酿酒成瘾，
they become alcoholics, and they refuse to have babies.
然后他们就不再生孩子。
That is why Russia is failing as a society.
这就是俄国社会衰败的原因。
Because slavery is being imposed on Russians by the Westerners,
西方人把奴役强加给俄国人，导致奴役被施加。
and the Russians refuse to be slaves.
俄国人却不愿成为奴隶。
But because this system, consumerism, is so perfect,
但因为这个系统，消费主义如此完美，
Russian people lack an understanding of how to rebel against the system,
俄罗斯人缺乏对如何反抗系统的理解，
and that's why Russia is falling apart.
这就是俄国正在崩溃的原因。
Okay? That is a Putin argument.
好的？这就是普京的论点。
Does that make sense? Okay?
这有道理吗？好的？
In other words, consumerism has corrupted the Russian soul.
换句话说，消费主义已经腐蚀了俄国灵魂。
And Russian have chosen to be corrupted by consumerism.
俄国人已选择被消费主义腐蚀。
Okay? So does it make sense?
好的？这样说有道理吗？
So what Vladimir Putin
那么弗拉基米尔·普京是怎样的呢？
must do is free his people.
必须做的就是解放他的人民。
Even though they may enjoy prison.
即使他们可能享受囚笼。
Okay? Even though Russians may enjoy slavery,
好吧？即使俄罗斯人可能享受奴役，
Putin is still going to free his people.
普京仍将解放他的人民。
And he's going to do it by creating a new concept to combat
他将通过创造一个新概念来对抗消费主义。
consumerism. Okay? So
好吧？
we've gone from the worker to the consumer,
我们已从工人转到消费者，
and Putin is going to introduce a new concept called the warrior.
普京将推出一个新概念叫战士。
The consumer is a person,
消费者是一个人，
an individual, who acts alone and
一个人，独自行动并
does so to preserve
以此来保
his or her life. Okay?
自己的生命。好吧？
The consumer is a coward.
消费者是懦夫。
The consumer lacks imagination.
消费者缺乏想象。
The consumer is alienated.
消费者已疏离。
The warrior is different.
战士不同。
The warrior is an individual who sees
战士是一个看到的个体，...
that through his actions,
...
he or she can shape the direction of history.
他或她能塑造历史的方向。
I can make my own reality through my courage
我可以凭勇气和想象力创造自己的现实。
and through my imagination.
And by acting with others.
并且与他人一起行动。
Okay? Does that make sense? Alright.
好？这样说通吗？好吧。
So, let's do another thought experiment to understand the warrior concept.
于是，让我们再做一次思维实验来理解战士概念。
Let's just say that, okay, in this school I give everyone a million dollars and now you hate each other.
我们先说，好的，在这所学校我给每个人一百万美元，然后你们互相仇恨。
Okay? Then what happens is I put you on a plane
好的？然后发生的事是我把你们放在一架飞机上
and I take you all to an island.
然后我把你们全部送到一个岛上。
Okay? And you're on this island and
好的？你们在这座岛上，且…
unfortunately on this island there are millions
不幸的是，在这座岛上有数百万…
and millions of flesh -eating monkeys.
以及数百万只吃肉的猴子。
They want to eat you.
它们想吃你。
Okay? But you hate each other.
好吧？但你们互相仇恨。
You don't want to work together. What happens now?
你们不想一起工作。现在会怎样？
What happens now? Yeah,
现在会怎样？
that's right. If you don't do anything, everyone gets eaten by a monkey, right?
对的。如果你不做任何事，大家都会被猴子吃掉，对吗？
But what are you going to do? How?
那你们打算怎么做？怎么做？
You will fight the monkeys by how will you fight the monkeys?
你将怎样打败猴子？
Okay. What's going to happen is that everyone is going to put aside
好了。接下来会发生的是大家把……放在一边
the differences and work together to fight the monkeys.
把差异化为共识，齐心协力打败猴子。
Okay? And how will you feel
好的？那你会怎么感觉？
in this process? Are you going to be happy or depressed?
在这个过程中？你会感到快乐还是沮丧？
You're going to be happy. Why? Exactly. You're all working towards the same goal.
你会感到快乐。为什么？正是如此。你们都在朝同一目标努力。
Okay? Structure, meaning, and purpose.
结构、意义与目的。
Okay? That's what war does.
好的？这就是战争的作用。
War gives you structure, meaning, and purpose so you feel happy about yourself.
战争给你结构、意义和目的，让你对自己感到快乐。
Okay? Now let's say that during this war,
好？现在假设在这场战争中，
um, like Celine dies.
嗯，就像塞琳去世一样。
Okay? Now what happens?
好的？现在发生了什么？
What does death do now?
死亡现在又做了什么？
Yeah. Yes.
是的。
And? So Celine dies.
然后呢？于是塞琳去世。
She goes to martyr. You all celebrate her, remember her.
她成了殉道者。你们都来纪念她，记住她。
You give her a great funeral. And then what do you do?
你给她办了大葬礼。然后呢？
You fight harder. Do you understand?
你更努力地战斗。你明白吗？
Because death gives you purpose.
因为死亡给你带来目的。
Her death makes your life much more valuable to you and to others.
她的去世让你的生命对你和他人都更有价值。
Okay? Not only do you celebrate her life,
好的？不只是庆祝她的生命，
but you celebrate her, your own life.
但你们庆祝自己的生命。
Okay? Alright.
好的？行了。
Now let's just say that the monkeys are coming.
现在就说猴子来了。
Okay? And there's a bridge.
好吧？还有一座桥。
There's a bridge. And
有一座桥。还有
Jack is standing on this bridge.
杰克站在这座桥上。
And there are ten of you on the other side.
还有十个人在另一边。
Okay? So Jack has a choice.
好吧？于是杰克有个选择。
He can either cut the bridge and kill himself
他可以砍桥自杀，救他人
and save the others, or he can run, run,
或者他可以跑，跑
and possibly all get killed.
并且可能全部被杀死。
Right? By the monkeys. What does Jack do?
对吧？被猴子们。杰克会怎么做？
For sure he will do this.
他一定会这么做。
What will he do? He's going to sacrifice himself.
他会怎样做？他要自我牺。
He's going to sacrifice himself. Okay? Do you understand? We've seen this in war over and over.
他要自我牺。好吧？你明白了吗？我们在战争里一次又一次看到这一点。
Okay? That's what war does to people.
好吧？这就是战争对人的作用。
It makes you, it gives you structure, meaning, and purpose.
它让你变得更强、更有纪律，给你结构、意义和目的。
And it makes you a stronger, more disciplined person.
它让你变得更强、更有纪律。
Okay? Does that make sense? Right?
好吧？这说得通吗？对吧？
So that's the thought experiment. So, in theory
于是就是这个思维实验。于是，理论上
then, when
然后，当
Putin launched this military operation,
普京发动这次军事行动时
it's called a special military operation in Ukraine back in February 2022,
它在2022年2月被称为乌克兰的特种军事行动
then we should see improvements in Russian society.
于是我们应该看到俄罗斯社会的改善。
Okay? Does that make sense? So,
好吧？这说得通吗？于是，
what's happened in Russia since this war?
自从这场战争以来，俄罗斯发生了什么？
Are people happier? Do you think people are happier?
人们更开心了吗？你觉得人们更开心吗？
Do you think people are happier now? Okay,
你觉得现在人们更开心吗？好吧，
I think they are. Do you think people are more unified?
我觉得他们是的。你觉得人们更团结吗？
I think they are. Okay? So one example of this is
我觉得是的。好吧？举个例子是
the Russian economy
俄罗斯经济
is surviving U.S.
正在承受美国
sanctions. In fact, it's getting stronger and stronger.
制裁。实际上，它正变得越来越强大。
Why? Because people are fully participating in the economy now.
为什么？因为人们现在完全参与了经济。
Okay? So, an example of this is that every month
好的？所以，举个例子是每个月
Russia is producing 150,000
俄罗斯每月生产150,000枚弹壳。好吧？
ammunition cells. Okay?
弹壳。好吧？
For the war. Every month,
用于战争。每个月，
Russia is producing more ammunition shells for the war.
俄罗斯正生产更多弹壳用于战争。
Okay? 150,000. Can you guys guess how much
好吧？150,000。你们能猜到美国每月生产多少吗？
the United States produces every month?
In comparison? Guess. Guess the number.
比起来？猜猜。猜个数字。
Jimmy? 100,000?
吉米？一十万？
2,000. Okay? You understand?
2000。好吧？你明白了吗？
So Russia is steering towards a war economy.
于是俄罗斯正朝着战时经济转型。
Factories are producing more and more weapons.
工厂产出越来越多的武器。
But that means more and more people are
这意味着越来越多的人……
employed. Which means that they're drinking less.
使用。也就是说他们喝酒更少。
Okay? When you have structure and meaning
好的？当你有结构和意义时。
and purpose in your society, all this goes down.
并且在你们社会里，所有这些都在下降。
Corruption goes down. Alcoholism goes down.
腐败下降。酿酒下降。
Oh, sorry. Fertility goes up.
哦，抱歉。生育率上升。
All right? Does that make sense?
好了？这样说对吗？
So, last year,
于是，去年，
Putin made this statement.
普京作出了这番话。
Okay? He was asked, okay,
好吧？他被问到，好的，
you have a lot of Russians dying on the battlefield.
你有很多俄罗斯人在战场上牺死。
And he said, well, when they die on the battlefield,
他又说，嗯，当他们在战场上牺死时，
we honor them.
我们就会纪念他们。
They sacrifice themselves for their country.
他们为国家献身。
They will always be remembered as heroes.
他们将永远被记作英雄。
Their families will always love them.
他们的家人永远爱他们。
But if we just let them do what they want,
但如果我们只是让他们按自己的意思去做，他们只会把自己喝死。
all they're gonna do is drink themselves to death.
好吧？你明白了吗？
Okay? You understand? So Putin is saying is
所以普京所说的是
that what war is, ultimately,
那场战争究竟是怎样的，
it is a mechanism for society to rejuvenate itself.
它是社会焕发自我的机制。
Okay? What war is,
好了？那场战争究竟是怎样的。
it's opportunity for society to cut away the fat.
这是社会削减肥肉的机会。
To make it more lean.
让它更精简。
So for Putin, this war is not really
所以对普京来说，这场战争并不是真正的
about conquering Ukraine or defending against NATO.
关于征服乌克兰还是抵御北约？
It's really about saving Russian civilization.
真正是为了拯救俄国文明。
It's really about saving the Russian soul.
真正是为了拯救俄国灵魂。
Okay? If you don't fight this war,
好的？如果你不打这场战争，如果你让这些趋势继续下去，那么俄罗斯最终会消失为一个民族国家。
and you let these trends continue, then Russia will eventually
cease to exist as a nation.
好的？如果你不打这场战争，如果你让这些趋势继续下去，那么俄罗斯最终会消失为一个民族国家。
Does that make sense? Okay?
这有道理吗？好吧？
So what's gonna happen is that over time,
那么接下来会发生的事是，随着时间的推移，
a new concept will arise to challenge consumerism
一个新的概念将会出现来挑战消费主义
and liberal democracy. And we will call this concept Putinism.
和自由民主。我们把这个概念叫做普京主义。
And the idea of Putinism is really continuous war.
普京主义的核心是持续的战争。
That as a society,
作为一个社会，
you should be constantly fighting wars in all order to discipline,
你应该不断在各个层面打仗以锻炼，统一你的民族。
unify your nation.
好的？并让你的人民更强壮。
Okay? And make your people stronger
and more prosperous.
和更繁荣。
That is Putinism.
那就是普京主义。
Okay? And I think this will be his defining legacy.
好的？我认为这将是他的定义性遗产。
And Putinism is a direct response to liberal democracy.
而普京主义是对自由民主的直接回应。
So we will shift as a society from one
于是我们作为社会将从一种
that is based on the consumer to one that is based on the warrior.
基于消费者的转为基于战士的。
Does that make sense, guys? Okay?
那有道理吗，大家？好吧？
Any questions?
还有问题吗？
Oh, so Selina asked a question.
哦，塞琳娜问了个问题。
How is capitalism different from liberal democracy?
资本主义与自由民主有什么区别？
That's a great question. So capitalism is only concerned about capital.
这真是个好问题。资本主义只关注资本。
So you can be a fascist country and be capitalistic.
你可以是个法西斯国家，也可以是资本主义的。
So capitalism, many people say, leads to fascism.
于是，很多人说资本主义会导致法西斯主义。
So Nazis were extremely capitalistic.
于是，纳粹党极度资本主义。
They see communism, the Soviet Union, as a direct threat
他们把共产主义、苏联视为直接威胁。
to its existence. Okay?
到它的存在。好吗？
The idea of a liberal democracy is the participation of everyone in
自由民主的想法是人人参与资本的生成。
the generation of capital.
Does that make sense? So in other words,
这有道理吗？换句话说，
this is one of the ironies of the 20th century is that
20世纪的一个讽刺是，
capitalism and democracy
资本主义与民主是两种对立的力量。
are opposing forces. And
是相互对立的力量。且
the idea of liberal democracy is to put the
自由民主的想法是把两者放在一起，合成一个合成体来解释。
two together in a synthesis as to explain away
or ignore the contradictions.
或忽略矛盾。
Okay? But capitalism and democracy are contradictions.
好的？但资本主义与民主是矛盾。
Does that make sense? Okay, any more questions?
这有道理吗？好的，还问什么？
Okay, so Jack makes a great point, which
好的，杰克说了个很好的点，
is like wars that have been fought before
像以前打过的战争一样
have destroyed societies.
已经毁灭了社会。
Okay? So think of Athens and Sparta.
好的吗？想想雅典和斯巴达。
And think of World War II and World War I.
再想想第二次世界大战和第一次世界大战。
Okay? Societies become exhausted and destroyed. So
好的吗？社会会疲惫并被毁灭。
the idea of continuous war is you fight small -scale wars
连续战争的想法是你要打一场小规模的战争
so as to manage the!
以此来管理！
!
！
the size of the conflict.
冲突的规模。
Okay? And it's important to do that.
好的吗？而且这很重要。
Why? Why don't you want a large -scale war?
为什么？你为什么不想要大规模战争？
No, no, no, no. You, what might happen in a large -scale war?
不，不，不，不。你，想想大规模战争会怎样？
That's right, okay. The problem is you have nuclear weapons in place now.
对，好的。问题是现在你们已经有核武器。
Okay? So it is not
好的？所以这点不是问题。
it's not smart to fight a large -scale war.
不打大规模战争是明智的。
When you fight a large -scale war you can't really control
打大规模战争时你无法真正控制升级。
the escalation. And eventually, say the United States
最终，美国会说……
and Russia fight a ground war in Europe, eventually they'll be so
当俄国在欧洲打一场陆战，最终他们互相激愤到要用核武器。
angry at each other, they might have to use nuclear weapons.
好的？这就是原因。
Okay? That's why
one of the major tenets of Putinism
普京主义的主要原则之一
is you pick small contained conflicts.
就是挑选小规模的局部冲突
So Ukraine is a small contained conflict.
所以乌克兰就是一个小规模的局部冲突
Okay? An invasion of France or an invasion of Britain would lead to nuclear war.
好的？法国或英国的入侵会引发核战争。
Does that make sense? Okay?
这有道理吗？好的？
And that's why the United States would also pick Iran.
这也是美国会挑选伊朗的原因。
Because Iran would be a small contained conflict.
因为伊朗会是一个小规模的局部冲突。
Does that make sense? Okay?
这有道理吗？好的？
So this is the Putinism.
这就是普京主义。
Okay? War is a mechanism to transform your society.
好的？战争是把社会转变的机制。
Whereas before, we understood war as a mechanism to conquer others.
之前我们把战争理解为征服他人的机制。
Okay? As imperialism or the spreading of civilization.
好的？作为帝国主义或文明传播的手段。
Now, the idea of Putinism is no, guys.
现在，普京主义的想法就是这样，伙计们。
We don't care about the other people.
我们不关心别人。
We care about ourselves. We're using war as
我们关心自己。我们把战争当作…
basically a mechanism to discipline our bodies.
基本是把我们的身体训练成纪律的机制。
Just like the gym. Okay?
就像去健身房。好的吗？
Does that make sense? Okay?
这样说通吗？好的吗？
The thing about global leaders,
关于全球领袖的事，
world leaders is they're all insane but they're not stupid.
世界领袖们都很疯狂，却不傻瓜。
You understand? There's a difference.
你懂了吗？有区别。
They're happy to kill millions of people.
他们乐意杀死数百万人。
They're not happy to blow up the world.
他们不乐意炸毁世界。
Okay? But
好的吗？
Jack's other point is that
杰克的另一个观点是
Russia's not a very wealthy country.
俄罗斯不是一个很富裕的国家。
Right? Eventually, you're going to exhaust yourself.
对吧？最终，你会把自己耗尽。
And that's why we think war is usually a pyramid scheme.
于是我们认为战争通常是金字塔式的计划。
Okay? And what that means is
好？这意味着什么呢？
so the example is Nazi Germany.
举例就是纳粹德国。
When they were fighting these wars,
当他们在这些战争中作战时，
it was costing their economy a lot of money so they were forced to fight even more wars.
那耗费了他们的经济大量资金，于是他们被迫再打更多战争。
Okay? That's what eventually led to Germany's invasion of Russia
好？这最终导致了德国入侵俄罗斯。
because they needed the resources and the manpower.
因为他们需要资源和人力。
Okay? And that's the same thing that will happen here
好？这和这里会发生的事一样。
where, okay, Putin is spending a lot of money to fight this war in Ukraine.
好，普京在乌克兰战争上花费了大量金钱。
Okay? But after he finishes this war in Ukraine,
好的？但在他在乌克兰结束这场战争后，
he needs to go conquer more territory for their resources.
他需要去征服更多领土以获取资源。
Okay? So in the long term,
好的？所以从长远来看，
this could lead to disaster.
这可能导致灾难。
Okay? This could lead to a large scale war.
好？这可能引发大规模战争。
But in the short term,
但短期内，
it does work. Okay?
它确实有效。好？
Does that make sense? Okay. Any more questions?
这样说通吗？好。还有别的问题吗？
Okay. So,
好。那，
Selena asked a great question, which is like eventually people are going to get exhausted.
塞莱娜提了个很好的问题，像是最终人们会精疲力竭。
Okay? And
好？然后
what Putin
什么是普京
believes is that
我认为是这样
the Russians are a warrior culture.
俄国人是个战士文化
Okay? Russians enjoy war.
好？俄国人喜欢战争。
Russians are good at war.
俄国人善于战争。
So, Russians won't be exhausted by war.
于是，俄国人不会因战争而疲惫。
They'll be galvanized and energized by war.
他们会因战争而被激励并充满活力。
That's a theory. Okay? And he's right.
那是一个理论。好？他是对的。
Okay? There are warrior cultures out there around the world
好的？世界各地都有战士文化，喜欢作战。
that do enjoy fighting.
好的？这些战士文化在世界各地都很活跃，喜欢作战。
Okay? So you think of the German people.
好的？你想到的是德国人。
Right? The Germans have been fighting wars for
对吗？德国人一直在打仗。
a thousand years and have been really good at it.
一千年，且一直做得很出色。
Okay? You think of Japanese.
好？你想到的是日本人。
Okay? Japan is also a warrior culture that enjoys fighting wars.
好？日本也是喜欢打仗的战士文化。
Okay? China is not a warrior culture.
好？中国不是战士文化。
It's very hard for the Chinese to fight wars.
对中国人来说，打仗很难。
And Chinese, okay, I hate to say this, but China would probably lose most wars.
而且中国人，好的，我说这句话很不情愿，但中国大概会输大多数战争。
Okay? It's not a warrior culture. So, for Chinese civilization,
好？它不是战士文化。所以，对中国文明来说，
war would be exhausting. But for Russian civilization,
战争会很累人。但对俄罗斯文明来说，
war can be energizing and
战争可以充满活力并
illuminating. Okay? Does that make sense? It depends on your civilization.
照亮的。好？
Okay? Any more questions? Okay.
好？还有问题吗？好。
So, um,
所以，呃，
what's going to happen? And the answer is that
接下来会发生什么？答案是……
um, culture works right now.
呃，文化现在正好发挥作用。
Okay? Because war culture beats consumer culture easily.
好的？因为战争文化很容易击败消费文化。
So you see the war in Ukraine where
所以你看到乌克兰的战争场景。
Russians are destroying the
俄罗斯人正在摧毁
Ukrainians and the Europeans are like ah, I'm too busy watching TV.
乌克兰人，欧洲人则像啊，我正忙着看电视。
I'm too busy buying things.
我正忙着买东西。
I'm too busy vacationing. Okay? So consumers don't want to go to war.
我正忙着度假。
Okay? But eventually Russia is going to reach a point
好的？但最终俄罗斯将达到一个直接威胁德国、法国和英国的节点。
where it directly threatens Germany and France and Britain.
And then they will
然后他们会
start to transition into a war culture.
开始转入战争文化。
Okay? So, Putinism will become the dominant ideology
好的？所以，普京主义将成为未来五十年的主导思想。
for the next 50 years.
好的？但普京主义可以传播到其他国家。
Okay? But Putinism can spread to other countries.
好的？所以，普京主义将成为未来五十年的主导思想。
Okay? So Japan can adopt Putinism.
好的？所以日本可以采用普京主义。
Germany can adopt it.
德国也可以采用。
Britain can adopt it. Okay?
英国也可以采用。
And so the world we call, so when this happens, we call this world
于是我们称之为……当这发生时，我们称之为这个世界
multipolar. So
多极化。于是
the word we use is multipolar.
我们使用的词是多极化。
Okay? Or multipolarity. Meaning that like there are different centers of power throughout the world.
好的？或者多极化。意思是世界各地有不同的权力中心。
Right now there's only the United States.
现在只有美国是中心。
It's a global hegemon. But
它是全球霸权。可是……
over the next 10, 20 years we expect a multipolar world where
在接下十、二十年里我们预期出现多极化世界
each region has different hegemons.
每个地区都有不同的霸权。
Okay? Does that make sense? Alright.
好？这样说通吗？好的。
Any more questions?.
还有问题吗？
..
……
Okay. So, what happens to the United States?
好的。那么，美国会怎样呢？
So next week we'll discuss the United States.
那么下周我们来讨论美国。
Okay? But what I will show you is that
好？但我接下来要给你展示的是
if the United States fights this war in Iran,
如果美国在伊朗打这场战争，
what it has to do is retreat back to its borders.
它要做的就是回到自己的边界
Okay? And has to become isolationist.
好的？然后就要变成孤立主义者。
But I'll explain that to you, I'll explain that to you next week.
我会在下周给你解释的。
Okay? Any more questions?
好的？还有别的问题吗？
Sorry, sorry. Go ahead.
抱歉，抱歉。请继续。
..
…
....
……
..
... Okay, so that's a great question, okay?
……好的，那是个很好的问题，好吗？
So we just said that consumer culture is the perfection of slavery,
于是我们刚才说，消费文化是奴役的完美形态。
but is warrior culture slavery?
但战士文化算是奴役吗？
And you can make the argument that it's actually anti -slavery.
并且你可以提出它实际上是反奴役的论点。
Why? Why?
为什么？为什么？
What can the warrior do that the consumer cannot do?
战士能做什么是消费者做不到的？
What's the problem with having a warrior culture, really?
拥有战士文化到底有什么问题？
See what I mean? What can warriors do that the consumers would never do?
你看我说的意思吗？战士能做什么是消费者做不到的？
Guys, warriors can rebel, right?
伙计们，战士能起义，对吧？
Warriors can mutiny. The army can be like, you guys are terrible.
战士能起兵。军队也会说，咱们这几个人真是糟糕。
We're going to rebel against you, okay?
我们要向你起义，好吗？
You understand? Does that make sense to you?
你明白吗？这对你来说有意义吗？
Consumers don't do that. Consumers are like, okay, we're going to do this.
消费者不会这么做。消费者会说，好吧，我们要这么做。
Hmm, I'm going to rebel.
嗯，我要起义。
I'm going to stop buying things.
我要停止买东西。
No one's going to do that, okay?
没人会这么做，好吗？
You will never be like, I'm going to stop buying things because I think it's bad for the environment.
你会说，我要停止买东西，因为我觉得对环境不好。
You won't do that. Whereas warriors are like, you know what?
而战士们会说，你知道吗？
I don't like this leader. Let's march to Moscow and get rid of him.
我不喜欢这个领导。我们去莫斯科，赶走他。
They can do that. And they do that all the time.
他们可以这么做。并且一直这么做。
That's why warrior culture is so destructive.
这就是战士文化如此破坏的原因。
That's why warrior culture was so dominant before and then we got rid of it.
这就是战士文化在之前如此占主导地位的原因，随后我们又把它除掉。
Because for political leaders,
因为对政治领袖来说，
warrior culture is a direct threat.
战士文化是直接威胁。
Does that make sense? Okay.
这有道理吗？好的。
So, but in this question,
所以，在这个问题上，
this reveals a contradiction in Putinism, okay?
这揭示了普京主义的矛盾，好的？
What is the ultimate problem in Putin turning
普京转变的终极问题是什么？
his entire country into a war society?
把整个国家变成战争社会？
What's the problem with that? And
这有什么问题？
it's a huge problem for Russia.
这对俄罗斯是个大问题。
And this is why ultimately Russia will not triumph in a multipolar world.
这就是为什么最终俄罗斯在多极世界中不会胜出的原因。
In fact, it will probably...
实际上它可能会崩溃……
Does it? Does it?
它会吗？它会吗？
It will probably fall apart. Why?
它可能会崩溃。为什么？
For a warrior culture to triumph, what does it need?
要让武士文化取得胜利，需要什么？
Warriors fight best when what?
战士最擅长的时机？
When there's a king, guys. When there's a king.
当有国王时，兄弟们。
That's why we have kings. Right?
那就是我们有国王的原因。对吗？
So what's the problem with Putin's Russia?
那普京的俄罗斯有什么问题？
Russia is a country of kings. What's going to happen to Russia?
俄罗斯是国王的国家。接下来会怎样？
What's going to happen to Russia? Guys, eventually Putin's going to die.
俄国会怎样？各位，普京最终会去世。
Do you understand? Eventually he's going to die.
你明白了吗？他最终会去世。
And then what's going to happen? The country's going to fall apart because
然后会怎样？国家将会分崩。
there's a warrior culture and you have these different generals fighting each other for total control.
有一种战士文化，你们有不同的将领互相争夺全局。
There's going to be civil war, okay?
将会有内战，明白吗？
Putin right now is a strategic genius.
现在的普京是战略天才。
He's the king. Everyone admires him.
他是王。人人敬仰他。
So he unites everyone. He can direct officers to war.
于是他统一了众人。他能指挥将士投入战斗。
He can direct the entire society into total war. When he dies, this society's going to fall apart.
他能把整个社会调入全军。等他去世，社会必将分崩。
Okay? That's why Putin's legacy will not be a strong Russia.
好的？这就是为什么普京的遗产不会是强大的俄罗斯。
It will be Putinism. Okay?
它将是普京主义。好吗？
The idea of continuous war. Russia may not survive without Putin.
持续战争的概念。没有普京，俄罗斯可能不再存续。
Okay? And
好的？还有
quite honestly, when you have a great leader like Putin, it's impossible to replace him.
说实在，像普京这样的大领袖，替代他的人根本没法出现。
All right? No one would have his genius and authority.
好了？没有人能拥有他的天才与权柄。
Right? Nothing like that.
对吧？没什么像那样的。
Nothing like that. Nothing like that.
没什么像那样的。没什么像那样的。
Nothing like that. Nothing like that. Nothing like that.
没什么像那样的。没什么像那样的。没什么像那样的。
Nothing like that.
没什么像那样的。
Nothing like that. Nothing like that. Nothing like that. Nothing like that. Nothing like that.
没什么像那样的。没什么像那样的。没什么像那样的。没什么像那样的。没什么像那样的。
Nothing like that. Nothing like that. Nothing like that.
没什么像那样的。没什么像那样的。没什么像那样的。
Nothing like that.
没什么像那样的。
Nothing like that. Nothing like that.
没什么像那样的。没什么像那样的。
Most people don't like to go to war, okay?
大多数人不喜欢去打仗，行吗？
Most people are scared by war.
大多数人被打仗吓着。
But ultimately, society is determined
但最终，社会由那些愿意根据自己的信念行动的人决定。
by those who are willing to act on their beliefs, okay?
所以当我们观察美国时，...
So when we looked at America,
look, they issue a lobby,
看，他们发起了游说，
they're only a small faction,
他们只是一个小派别，
small fraction of the American population, like less than 1%, okay?
美国人口中只有小小的一部分，不到1%。
But because they're willing to act, and they're organized, and they're determined,
但因为他们愿意行动，并且组织有序，且决意已定，
they're willing to act their way. Does that make sense? Same thing in Russia, where
他们就会按自己的方式行动。这样说对吗？在俄国也是如此，
at most, okay, I would say at most, you have 10%
至多为十个百分点，我想说至多是十%
who are like, oh, Putinism is a great idea, let's go conquer the world.
他们会说：噢，普京主义是个好主意，咱们去征服世界吧。
At most you have 10%. Most people are like,
至多只有10%。大多数人会这么想，
we want peace, we want to live our lives.
我们想要和平，想过自己的生活。
I have children, I want my children to be safe.
我有孩子，我想让孩子们安全。
I don't want to send my children to war, okay?
我不想把孩子送去打仗，好吗？
But again, history is determined by those
但历史还是由行动者决定。
who are determined to act and act in unison.
他们决定行动并同步行动。
Okay, so it's usually the most extreme individuals who get their way.
通常是最极端的人实现他们的目标。
Does that make sense? Okay, but thanks for the question, okay?
这样说通吗？谢谢你的提问。
Any more questions?.
还有问题吗？
Okay, so Putin believes that
好的，普京认为
Russia is first and foremost a great civilization,
俄罗斯首先是一个伟大的文明
okay? But as a great civilization,
好的？但作为一个伟大的文明，
it also has to fight wars to protect itself,
它也必须打仗来保全自身，
you understand? So Putin's like,
你明白吗？所以普京是这样想的。
you know what, if America left us alone,
你知道吗，如果美国让我们自己去做事，我们就不会打仗，行吗？
we would not fight wars, okay?
它只是因为美国坚持把我们包围。
It's only because America insists on encircling us,
It's only because Americainsists on encircling us,
insists on trying to destroy our culture, our civilization,
坚持要摧毁我们的文化，我们的文明
that we must fight a war.
我们必须打一场战争。
Okay, does that make sense?
好的，这有道理吗？
All right, and so what people say is, listen,
好了，大家听着，大家说的都是……
the war in Ukraine, it's ultimately caused
乌克兰的战争，最终是由……造成的
by NATO encroachment into Russia,
由北约侵入俄国而来，
right? So NATO,
对吧？所以北约，
after Soviet Union fell, expanded five times.
在苏联解体后，北约扩张了五次。
Guys, NATO was set up as a defensive alliance
伙计，北约本来是个防御同盟。
against the Soviet Union. Well, if you don't have a Soviet Union, you don't need NATO anymore.
对抗苏联。好吧，若你没有苏联，北约也就不需要了。
So why is NATO expanding?
那为什么北约还在扩张？
In fact, NATO was gonna expand into Ukraine.
实际上，北约将扩张到乌克兰。
So Putin is like, we are fighting this war,
于是普京说，咱们正在打这场战争
ultimately, to defend our civilization.
最终，为了捍卫我们的文明。
That's what matters, the defense of our civilization.
这才是关键，捍卫我们的文明。
And if it requires us into going,
如果它需要我们去行动，
if it requires us to go to war, then
如果它需要我们投入战争，
we will do so, okay?
我们就这么做，行吗？
And this is this process that will create Putinism, okay?
这就是将形成普京主义的过程，行吗？
Or continuous war. Does that make sense?
或者持续战争？这样说对吗？
Okay, any more questions? Yeah?
好的，还有别的问题吗？嗯？
Yeah?. Okay, so even though
嗯？ 好的，算了，就算是这样吧。
only 10% agree with Putinism,
只要10%的人认同普京主义，
I actually don't know the real number, okay?
我其实不知道确切数字，行吗？
But I think it's only a minority. What happens is that,
但我认为只是少数。发生的是，
in war, people become much more unified,
在战争中，人们会更团结，
okay? So the example is Ukraine, where actually,
好吧？所以例子是乌克兰，实际上，
about 50% of the people in Ukraine were Russian speakers.
约有五成乌克兰人说俄语。
Okay? And there was a large group of people,
好吧？还有一大批人……
at least a third, who were sympathetic towards Russia.
至少三分之一，倾向俄罗斯的人。
But the moment that Putin invaded,
但普京发动进攻的那一刻，
they all united under Zelensky, okay?
他们都在泽连斯基之下团结起来，行吗？
So that's what war does. War unifies people.
于是战争的作用就是如此。战争让人们团结。
So again, back to the island example.
再回到岛屿的例子。
You guys may hate each other when you land on the island.
你们在岛上登陆时可能互相厮杀。
But hey, if there's a million flesh -eating monkeys that wanna kill you,
不过，假如有一百万人类食猴想杀你们，
you guys are going to become a family.
你们就会变成一家人。
Okay? Does that make sense? Okay.
好的？这样说通吗？好的。
Any more questions? Is this clear to you guys?
还有问题吗？这对你们来说清楚吗？
Okay. You look at,
好的。你们看着，
so you wanna ask a question. question. Are you confused by something,
那么你想问个问题。问题。你是被什么弄糊涂了吗，
Celine? Excuse me?
塞琳？请问一下？
Okay, so again Russia is a warrior culture.
好了，再说一次，俄罗斯是个战士文化。
It enjoys war, it's good at fighting wars, okay?
它喜欢战争，善于打仗，好的？
But China is not a warrior culture.
但中国不是战士文化。
And the reason why is that throughout most of Chinese history,
原因是，在中国历史的大部分时期，
China was the dominant power, the hegemon, okay?
中国是主导力量，霸权，好的？
Also, China is surrounded by natural defenses, right?
另外，中国被自然防御环绕，没错吧？
So to the east you have the sea,
于是向东你有大海，
to the south and to the west you have mountains,
向南和向西你有山脉，向北你有长城，好的？
to the north you have the Great Wall, okay?
于是向东你有大海，向南和向西你有山脉，向北你有长城，好的？
So China doesn't feel threatened by anyone and therefore it doesn't have a warrior culture.
Does that make sense? But
这有道理吗？但
Russia is a huge country that's been invaded multiple times
俄罗斯是个大国，曾多次被侵略
and all these invasions were traumatic for Russia,
这些侵略都给俄罗斯带来创伤
okay? So you look at the German invasion of the Soviet Union in 1941,
好的？那么你看看1941年德国入侵苏联的情况，
that killed 20 million people.
那场战争造成两千万人死亡。
Millions of Russians died in that war and
数百万俄罗斯人死于那场战争。
people still celebrate that war, okay?
人们仍然庆祝那场战争，好吗？
So China is not a warrior culture,
所以中国不是战士文化，
okay?
好的？
Does that make sense? Okay, any more questions?
这样说通吗？
Okay, so
好的，接下来
what we will do next
我们要做的事是
week is we'll talk about Putin's strategic genius,
本周我们将讨论普京的战略天才，
okay? And what I will show you, and
好？我接下来要给你展示的内容是
this will be interesting, is that the way
这将会很有趣，俄罗斯人看世界的方式与我们截然不同。
that Russians see the world is radically different from the way we see the world,
that Russians see the world is radicallydifferent from the way we see the world,
okay? So
好？那么
we'll discuss Putin's
我们来讨论普京的
strategy moving forward next class, okay?
策略向前推进，下节课，好吗？
Does that make sense? Alright, good.
这样说通吗？好的，明白了。